Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Dummy Line ready for Anaya
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Majesty, Her Majesty has arrived.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Have a seat.
Yes.
Why did you come so late tonight?
Is there something urgent?
Your Majesty left in a hurry earlier today.
I forgot to ask ...
Lantern Festival is just around
the corner after New Year's Eve.
How would Your Majesty like to celebrate it this year?
The Empress Dowager has not yet recovered.
I don't want extravagance.
A simple celebration should suffice.
Your Majesty has awarded Hongxuan
a title as a grace of the new year.
Your benevolence will accumulate good fortune.
It was Concubine Sourire who reminded me.
She hopes I will bestow some mercy
on the lineage of Yun-e.
I have something to say but
I am not sure if it's appropriate.
There should be no reservation between us.
Yes ...
It just occurred to me as Your Majesty spoke.
Your Majesty,
although Concubine enjoys high favor,
she has overstepped boundaries at times.
I thought you have always liked her.
What's the matter?
Because I think highly of Concubine Sourire
and she will soon be promoted to Consort,
I must say so.
Your Majesty said Concubine Sourire
mentioned awarding a title to Hongxuan.
Although I am pleased with her compassion,
I worry that she shouldn't pass comment on state affairs.
Hongxuan's issue is also family-related.
Of course.
However, the rebellion of Yun-e is a state affair.
Family issues and state affairs are interwoven.
I'm afraid that Concubine Sourire might be exploited
because of her kindness.
And she might be unaware of the consequences.
In that way,
Concubine Sourire thinks in the same line as her father.
They both have sympathy for people I dislike.
I like Concubine Sourire for her intelligence.
But when it comes to appropriateness
and adherence to duty in the harem,
Noble Lady An and Noble Lady Délice
do much better than Concubine Sourire.
Noble Lady Délice is quite sensible indeed.
After all, Lady Délice is from our Manchu families,
unlike Concubine Sourire,
carrying the blood of the Han people.
She cannot have the same heart and mind with us.
Of course,
"Only the passage of days reveals a person's heart."
Concubine Sourire may do better in the future.
Peace to Imperial Mother.
Sit here.
Imperial Mother, how's your health recently?
Just the same as before.
Do you like the new Noble Lady, Délice?
She is the daughter of a meritorious official.
Don't be cold to her.
I understand.
The methods of balance apply to harem and court.
You can certainly handle them appropriately.
I will carefully remember your advice, Imperial Mother.
With the precedent of Yun-e,
I have been prudent in awarding the meritorious officials.
I did not grant them much real power
and will not favor their daughters too much.
That's good.
Since the incident with Nian Gengyao,
my heart has been constantly vigilant.
I hope that Longkodo
will not follow Nian Gengyao's path.
He doesn't dare.
I hope so.
But Imperial Mother, you've been in the harem so long
that you aren't clear about his mind anymore.
I have known Longkodo for decades,
and watched as he expended his thoughts
and energy for the late emperor and you.
Imperial Mother, haven't you always said
that concubines shouldn't interfere with state affairs?
You need not worry about state affairs.
You only need to take care of your health.
I still have unfinished tasks at court.
I am going back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I will visit you at dusk, Imperial Mother.
All right.
Look after yourself while you are busy with state affairs.
Yes.
His Majesty departs.
Did you sense from his words that
"The hound will be killed once the rabbit has been caught?"
I sensed so last time.
Your Majesty is benevolent to all under Heaven.
But Your Majesty needs to focus on your health
and cannot attend to everything of concern.
Besides, Longkodo did contribute
his effort to pacifying Nian Gengyao.
Everyone has their own fortune.
There's no one that I can care for.
Bamboo,
light up my hookah [or bong, or water pipe].
Hasn't this book been banned by Your Majesty?
Why is there one in the Hall of Mental Cultivation?
Although it is banned, I also must review it.
I need to know what these
outrageous people have been thinking.
What do you think of this book?
Flattering and fawning.
I had the author, Wang Jingqi,
beheaded and his head hung in public,
to warn his potential followers.
Your Majesty, please don't say that.
It scares me.
What are you afraid of?
Death is not a pity for Wang Jingqi's offense.
But hanging his head in public
would mostly terrify innocent people.
I also heard that
Your Majesty exiled his wife and son to be slaves,
and even discharged his distant relatives from office.
What do you think?
Wang Jingqi was punished for his crime
but his family and even relatives
are somewhat innocent.
If this raises discontent widely,
I would feel unworthy for Your Majesty.
You think I did wrong?
I dare not.
I just think that
many more would feel grateful for Your Majesty
if "major issues are reduced to minor ones
and minor ones to nothing."
You are a woman living in a chamber.
You don't understand men's determination.
For those who threaten my sovereignty,
I would rather be mistaken than sparing.
Otherwise,
I am putting my country at risk.
Yes, pardon my remark.
The Palace of Pearl Jade has been restored.
You should move back there.
I am just worried that Lady Délice has been upset.
She has to live with Consort Astuce,
inconvenient for Your Majesty to visit.
I have thought about it.
I think it's better that you live alone
in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I didn't like Noble Lady Délice
being around when I was with you.
Then, I shall be the only one in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
When the spring comes,
we can savor liqueurs in front of
the flowering crabapples in the yard.
When the snow-white pear flowers
cover the ground, I will dance the Startled Swan.
In the summer heat, we can shelter
together in the shade of the trees.
In the autumn, I will join you to make osmanthus wine.
In the winter, we can watch a sky of blowing snow.
I will always be by your side, and so will you.
I will always be with you, Si Lang.
Sourisse ...
Sourisse, are you there?
Si Lang.
I am here.
My Lady, Lady An has been waiting for you
outside since early this morning.
How long has she been waiting?
For about two hours.
I will hurry. I can't let her wait even longer.
Lingrong, so early!
Peace to you, Sourire.
I came here
so we can go to pay respects to Her Majesty together.
I will go to court.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Sourisse,
come tonight as usual.
Let's go.
You two have come early.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
We should always be early to pay our respects.
You both have the etiquette that deserves your promotions.
No wonder His Majesty favors you both.
I can't compare with Sourire's favor.
This morning, as I waited outside
the Hall of Mental Cultivation
for Sourire to join me in paying respects to Your Majesty,
I hadn't expected that I would be an inconvenience.
Lingrong.
Don't be shy, Sourire.
Her Majesty has been so tender to us.
This morning,
I heard His Majesty gave Sourire a new nickname.
Sourisse.
Your Majesty, please don't listen to Lingrong.
Sourisse ...
Sourisse!
Sourire is your honorary name.
His Majesty must favor you dearly
that he calls you by that.
I was just having a loose tongue.
Please forgive me, Sourire.
I will never do this again.
In the palace, we are a family.
Such teasing will be tolerated.
By the way,
Noble Lady An will have a rather simple
promotion ceremony as a Concubine.
While Concubine Sourire, you will need to wait.
Also, the robe you will wear at the ceremony,
I feel that it needs some further revision.
But don't worry.
I will have it sent to your palace on the day of your ceremony.
I thank Your Majesty.
Such a large scar! It's unpleasant to look at.
It has finally become scarred.
Looking unpleasant is nothing
compared to so much festering.
I worried so much about that.
Lingrong gave me this Scar Relief Gel.
It's the most effective.
I was scratched by the cat.
And see?
There is no scar now at all.
Absolutely.
But your wound was small.
This scar is so large.
The gel may not be that effective.
I have more in my palace.
You can try this one.
If it's effective,
I can ask Lingrong to make some more.
My Lady, Dr. Wen is here
for your routine pulse-taking.
Show him in quickly.
Yes.
You don't like the tedious routine
of pulse-taking. And you refused it.
So, you see, he has been getting on my case.
The gel is fragrant. It must be really good quality.
Peace to My Ladies.
Please rise.
Dr. Wen obeys the etiquette strictly
that he will never let himself miss a bow.
You are always teasing him.
My Lady, I wonder what this is.
This is the Scar Relief Gel.
May I have a look?
Is there anything wrong with it?
I have used several boxes of this gel.
I haven't felt anything strange.
I can't confirm in such a short time.
May I take this with me to examine it?
Of course. Please give it a thorough check, Dr. Wen.
You said that Qian Mingshi has a poem collection
named as Aromatic Ancient Pavilion.
And this is the collection.
I know this book from Mr. Zhen.
He saw this collection and kind of appreciated it.
So, he brought it home.
But to my knowledge,
Qian Mingshi and Nian Gengyao
both passed the imperial examination
of the 38th year of Emperor Kangxi.
And they had a close relationship.
Since Qian Mingshi is a close friend
of the sinful rebel Nian Gengyao,
it would be unsurprising if this was
a book of disrespect to Your Majesty.
So, how did Zhen Yuandao get a copy?
Was it available on Chessboard Street?
This collection hasn't been published.
I'm afraid that only close friends of
Qian Mingshi can access it.
I saw Mr. Zhen had this collection in his home,
so I went through all my sources to obtain this copy.
Zhen Yuandao never had any contact with Nian Gengyao.
I know this clearly.
I think likewise.
Maybe Mr. Zhen is only in contact with Qian Mingshi,
and has no relations with Nian Gengyao.
Even so, Mr. Zhen's keeping this collection
could have obscure meanings, I'm afraid.
Go on.
In this collection,
"He ruled Shaanxi as well as Zhaobo of Zhou Dynasty, and
defeated enemies miraculously like General Huo of the Western Han."
And also
"A monument should be built next to Emperor Kangxi's
memorial to scribe Nian's achievements in Tibet."
These two lines are not only flattering Nian Gengyao,
their following lines make the utmost effort
to praise the expeditions by Lord XIV and Lord X
who are now confined by Your Majesty.
Do you suggest that Zhen Yuandao keeps this collection
because he sympathizes Lord X and Lord VIX?
I don't know whether Mr. Zhen sympathizes Lord XIV,
but Concubine Sourire has pleaded Your Majesty
to grant a title to the son of Lord X.
This is known by the entire harem.
Even Noble Lady Délice has told me
about this act of kindness.
Emin.
Your Majesty.
You have had a good relationship with
Zhen Yuandao as his colleague.
Why do you report this to me?
I am Mr. Zhen's colleague,
and I do have a good relationship with him.
But I am graced by Your Majesty's favor.
I'm only devoted to serving Your Majesty.
I dare not be distracted by any personal relations.
Good.
You may leave.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Bring Concubine Sourire here to see me.
Yes.
No.
I will go see her in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Yes.
Did His Majesty said anything when
your father met with him?
I sent servants to ask my father carefully.
But His Majesty said nothing
after my father reported this matter.
He wasn't angry in the slightest?
My father said he couldn't tell.
Your Majesty, maybe my father didn't get to the point.
Since the settlement of Nian Gengyao, His Majesty has been vigilant of meritorious officials
and resentful about sympathizers of his enemies.
Nian Gengyao and Yun-e have paid their price for
pitying Yunsi and Yuntang.
Let alone a newly-promoted official
who embraces disloyal intentions.
But His Majesty didn't blame
Zhen Yuandao and Concubine Sourire.
That's exactly what I'm worried about.
I‘ve been with His Majesty for decades.
I know his temperament best
apart from the Empress Dowager.
I'm worried that His Majesty has changed
his temperament because of Concubine Sourire.
That would be intractable.
Concubine Sourire will soon be
promoted to Consort, Your Majesty.
Yes, at this young age.
I'm old as a yellow pearl.
I might have to abdicate the throne one day.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You've just moved back.
So I came to see you.
Your Majesty, the Palace of Pearl Jade
was restored so well.
I feel that it's too extravagant for me.
You will be promoted to Consort soon.
Your palace deserves to be conditioned
to suit your status.
Your Majesty, please have some tea to warm up.
I've got a poem anthology.
And I thought you should have a look.
Who is Qian Mingshi?
Just read the poems.
They are not that good.
The poems are not good
and the book is not easily available.
Who do you think will keep a copy?
Likely those who really appreciate the poems
or friends of the poet.
Why did Your Majesty ask me this?
Nothing.
I just think these poems exhausted words of flattery
to extol evils,
The poet should also be suspended and exiled.
I didn't read these poems carefully.
I found them uninteresting.
But I didn't see any extolling of evils.
The poet was praising Yun-e.
Were these written recently?
Or back when Yun-e was State Prince Dun?
The latter.
When he held the title State Prince Dun,
it's only natural that so many people adulated him.
Such anthologies must have existed in profusion.
Then how do you think I should deal with the poet?
I dare not comment.
Speak your mind.
I won't mind.
Circumstances have changed as time passed.
There's no need to bring the poet to account.
Destroying the poems will be enough.
As for those who collect them ...
If severe punishments were imposed on them,
people would think that
Your Majesty wouldn't let it go.
It's better to have the poems dissipating like clouds
rather than growing fear in people's hearts.
Well said.
I'll give more thought to it.
All right.
You will be having your promotion ceremony soon.
Rest well.
I will go check on Lady Délice.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
We congratulate Your Highness on your
promotion to Consort Sourire.
You may rise.
I thank Your Highness.
Jade, go and see the master of ceremony off.
Don't forget to give him some gifts.
Your Highness, remember to receive your instructions from the Empress after the ceremony,
and thank Their Majesties too.
The master of ceremonies has told me.
Vermilion, get my robe.
Right away.
Let's spread it out!
How exquisite!
Oh no!
This... This...
How can this be?
The ceremonial robe is considered
a reward from His Majesty.
It cannot be damaged.
If discovered, this will be an offense to His Majesty.
Where's Chief Jiang from The Household Department?
He just brought the presents. He's still in the yard.
Call him in.
Go quickly!
Chief Jiang, look.
It's my mistake. I will accept Your Highness's punishment.
Chief Jiang, this robe sent from the
Household Department was damaged.
You can't escape the responsibility if His Majesty investigates.
But I didn't bring you here to punish you.
I was hoping we could find a solution together.
Your Highness,
this robe was woven from gold and
silver threads by several weavers.
There was only enough thread to tailor this one.
We would have to open the warehouse
if we wish to repair it.
It will not only draw a lot of attention,
but also may take two to three days.
Two or three days? We don't have so much time.
Exactly.
I have to go thank Their Majesties right away.
Your Highness, we can't stay for much longer.
Their Majesties would also blame us if we were late.
Your Highness, I have a possible plan
for this urgent situation.
What is it?
A few days ago, the Empress sent over a robe for repairs.
It quite follows the protocol of a ceremonial robe.
Although it doesn't resemble this one,
it may be an appropriate substitute.
Are you sure?
The style of that robe is quite old.
It was probably used by Her Majesty before.
But they haven't collected the mended robe for 2 days.
It might be our only option.
If so, you should go get it!
Yes.
Although Her Majesty's robe is a bit old, it is still resplendent.
Let's hurry, My Lady. Don't let
Thier Majesties wait for too long.
This robe does fit Your Highness very well.
But it looks so familiar somehow.
I might have seen it somewhere before.
Really?
No time to worry about that. Let's go to
the Palace of Great Benevolence.
Yes, let's go.
It's all my fault, Your Majesty,
to be having a migraine all of a sudden.
I'm worried if I will miss the auspicious hour.
No worries, you can go when you're feeling better.
Your Majesties,
Her Highness Consort Sourire has arrived.
Would Your Majesty mind going first?
I will be right behind you.
Sure, I will go out first.
Sourisse...?
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Sourisse, why didn’t you call me Si Lang?
Si Lang.
Sourisse!
Sourisse ...
You've finally come back to me.
Zhen Huan
bows in respect before Your Majesty.
Why it is you?
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Where did you get this robe?
How dare you!
Your Majesty.
How could this happen?
Spring! How could this happen?
Several days ago, when Her Majesty
was sorting out Empress Première’s clothes,
two southern pearls were found to have come off this robe.
And the threads were loose, too.
So Her Majesty asked me to send it
to The Household Department.
I had wanted to take the time to bring it back.
But I forgot to do so among
other tasks in the past few days.
I don’t know
why this robe would be on Concert Sourire.
I beg Your Majesties’ forgiveness.
I do beg Your Majesties’ forgiveness.
How foolish!
How many times have I told you
that Empress Première’s belongings must be kept with care?
And my command passed like
a puff of wind through your ears!
It could be any other garment...
But it had to be this one!
This is what she wore when she first met me.
Your Majesty still remembers ...
this is the robe that my sister wore
the first time she came to visit me.
I will never forget.
Take it off.
It was my negligence.
I didn’t realize that I am wearing
Empress Première’s old robe by mistake.
Consort Sourire is always careful.
She certainly did not intend this.
Explain... Why has this happened?
Before I came to Your Majesty’s palace,
I found that my ceremonial robe was torn.
So I borrowed this robe from
The Household Department.
I didn’t know the origin of the robe.
I would never intend to offend Empress Première.
I beg Your Majesty's forgiveness.
Consort Sourire, she...
She…
Consort Sourire?
Although she has had the conferring ceremony,
she hasn’t listened to your teaching,
and therefore the conferral is not completed.
The Palace of Pearl Jade has been well repaired.
You can stay there and ponder upon your fault.
His Majesty's order:
The Palace of Pearl Jade will be shut
and no one is allowed to enter or leave.
Who are you? What's going on?
Chief Jiang was flogged to death by His Majesty's order.
I am the new chief of The Household Department.
Attention!
Yes.
Shut the gate!
Yes!
No!
What is happening? What are you doing?
Be insolent if you dare,
at the cost of your own heads.
Yes, Chief Gou.
Don't disturb My Lady.
Madam, what should we do?
Your Highness ...
They locked up the Palace of Pearl Jade,
didn't they?
Yes.
My Lady, don't be too sad,
for the good of your health.
It's all right.
At least I can have some peace now.
I'm sorry that I dragged you all into this ordeal.
We don't mind.
Jinxi...
I once asked you
why you became so loyal to me.
You said it's the force of destiny.
Can you tell me the real reason now?
It's because I resemble Empress Première.
Isn't it?
My Lady, you do somewhat resemble the Empress Première.
But not very much.
Really?
I just realized today
why Consort Honnête seemed so surprised
when she first saw me.
And why she would say I was a reminiscence.
She is one of the most senior
concubines in the palace.
She must have known Empress Première well.
The half resemblance in appearance and personality
is enough to capture His Majesty's heart.
Half resemblance ...
in appearance and personality
is enough to capture your loyalty, isn't it?
No.
Your loyalty is dedicated to Empress Première.
Your Highness.
Your Highness is overthinking.
I wasn't fortunate enough to serve Empress Première.
But she helped me once out of pity by chance.
My Lady,
you only bear some true resemblance to
Empress Première when you put on her clothes.
Empress Première was too kind.
My Lady, although you are also soft-hearted,
you can be decisive when necessary.
I began to devote my loyalty to you, My Lady,
partly because I'm grateful for Empress Première's mercy.
But after that, it was only because of you.
Now I've lost His Majesty's favor.
I'm afraid there is no turn around like before.
Your dedication would only be futile.
My Lady.
I'm also at fault for what happened today.
I felt that dress was familiar,
but I failed to recall that it belonged to Empress Première.
Mr. Jiang also had never served Empress Première.
It looks like we have fallen into another trap again.
Poor Mr. Jiang has been flogged to
death by His Majesty's order.
I'm not sure if he was implicated by me
or simply used as a pawn.
Jinxi...
I should not have doubted your loyalty.
Even if you are dedicated to me due to Empress Première,
you did everything for my benefit.
But His Majesty...
Empress, oh the Empress...
You really have tried your utmost.
My Lady, why do you think so?
Who else can access Empress Première's clothes
without the Empress's instruction?
How can it be so coincidental!
"The mantis catches the cicada, but the oriole is behind."
I'm just another pawn to the Empress.
My Lady, you had no intention of
impinging Her Majesty's authority.
However, your continued promotion and
high favor must have made her wary.
I have lost favor from His Majesty and the Empress.
More importantly, this incident involves Empress Première.
That is the wound on His Majesty's mind.
It seems that
there is no immediate turnabout right now.
We can only wait for the right time.
The right time?
Right now, right here;
How is it different from the Cold Palace?
My Lady.
His Majesty, in order to protect me
from the rivalries in harem and court,
sent me to Penglai Island.
He did it out of deep affection.
But my confinement today is not comparable.
Forget it.
Sourire...
In the eyes of His Majesty,
I'm only a substitute for Empress Première.
My Majesty hasn't eaten anything all night.
Please have some tea to refresh yourself.
How dare you!
All of you!
Inform The Household Department
that Concubine Sourire will
only be provided for as an Attendant.
Yes, Your Majesty
Your Majesty, how is the pressure？
I heard His Majesty got angry
in the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
He should be angry.
When his most favored concubine made a big mistake,
how could His Majesty not be angry？
But just for a piece of clothing,
His Majesty wouldn’t be like this.
Empress Première is the most
unforgettable person of His Majesty.
And Lady Délice’s father has worked hard in advance.
His Majesty was already irked by Concubine Sourire.
Première, you are really my good sister.
Even after so many years of death,
you can still help me and protect me.
It seems Concubine Sourire has
really angered His Majesty this time.
But Chief Jiang was implicated.
Those who know too much will never live too long.
Your Majesty.
I will put forth my best effort to serve Your Majesty.
I know your thoughts.
Rise.
Yes.
Although Concubine Sourire is grounded,
I worry that His Majesty’s anger will only be temporary.
If His Majesty favors her again,
I'm afraid it will be a waste of all the effort.
This time, however much His Majesty would pity her,
I'm afraid Concubine Sourire is not turning back.
Concubine Sourire is not a person to swallow her pride.
How can she reconcile herself
when she realizes that all these years of affection
is all because of her being a substitute?
Your Majesty's effort
turned out to be extinguishing her hope.
I admire Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, Lady Vertu requests an audience.
Is she here for Concubine Sourire?
Probably. She’s very anxious.
I don’t want to see her. Give her a reason to leave.
Yes.
Lady Vertu, Her Majesty had a migraine attack.
She is already asleep after taking some medicine.
When Her Majesty wakes up, please inform
Her Majesty of my request for an audience.
Certainly.
When Her Majesty is better,
I will definitely inform her.
Lunar, let’s go to the Palace of Longevity.
My Lady,
I'm afraid the Empress Dowager is already asleep.
I couldn't see His Majesty, nor Her Majesty.
What else can I do if I don’t ask
the Empress Dowager for help?
The Empress Dowager has been unwell.
It’s not good to disturb her at this time.
It’s too cold outside,
you might as well go tomorrow, My Lady.
I can’t worry about that.
Let’s go to the Palace of Longevity!
My Lady!
My Lady.
Madam, is Her Majesty asleep?
Her Majesty isn't,
but she wouldn't spare time to see you.
Why?
Her Majesty doesn’t want to see me?
Madam, may I trouble you once more
to inform Her Majesty of my request?
Her Majesty asked me to tell you,
My Lady, it’s freezing outside
but your mind has not cooled down.
But Concubine Sourire is my sister!
I grew up with her!
Her Majesty said that no matter who it is,
you will do something wrong with an impulsive mind.
Before arriving at the Palace of Longevity,
you must have visited the Hall of Mental Cultivation
and the Palace of Great Benevolence.
Since both palaces did not respond to your request,
there is no need for Her Majesty to see you, My Lady.
My Lady, please take your leave.
Madam…
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.